Today's דף daf of אלו טריפות Elu Tereifos which has been a
wonderful פרק perek in terms of not only טריפות treifos but כשר
kosher and non-כשר non-kosher species of birds and fish and grasshoppers and
we are ending with a discussion of the grasshoppers. So today's דף
daf is ס"ז Samech Zayin sixty-seven and we pick up at the
very bottom of ס"ו עמוד ב'. Samech Vav Amud Bet So let's
take a look there.
The גמרא Gemara says the following. We had been discussing the issue
that you only need the כשר סימנים kosher simanim, for things that
are found in oceans and and rivers and so on but for
types of water insects because חז"ל Chazal were certainly very aware of
the fact that if you took well water or other types of
water you know there'd be all these tiny little bugs and insects
in it that for those types of things because it's not doesn't
fit the biblical verse of oceans and rivers it doesn't matter if
they have the כשר kosher or non-כשר kosher סימנים. simanim Now of
course an interesting question could be raised about you know what if
it happens to be not even insects what if it happens to
be like if it's well water and like some actual sea creature
came up through the you know whatever is feeding the well the
aquifer I mean I think that those things can happen. Cave fish.
Uh-huh. Cave fish. Okay and that's like a standing water like a
pond type of a thing or I guess not a river. Are
you saying K or cave?
Cave. Cave. Okay cave.
So you know that's an interesting question but part of the answer
is is that there's two things here that inform this that we
will see at the towards later in the דף. daf. One is
is that this might not be that much more than a instantiation
of this general principle that we've seen earlier about שרץ השרץ על
הארץ sheretz hashoretz al ha'aretz that if you find a bug in
a fruit or vegetable it's also surprisingly not a problem as long
as it it it grew within the fruit and vegetable and never
it was exposed to the ground it never crawled on the ground.
So why what well we'll talk about whether it's on the tree
later that was שמואל's Shmuel statement we'll talk about that. Okay okay
we'll talk about all
that let me
let me finish with the intro okay. Let me finish with the
intro. Okay. So in a way I understand in a way we're
saying something similar here that insects that grow naturally within the water
are not a problem about water insects. However here it's different because
the גמרא Gemara is distinguishing between sort of insects or sea creatures
or whatever that's grown first of all what's the difference between an
insect and a sea creature right? I mean the תורה Torah calls
them all a שרץ sheretz so if you've got an eel or
a crab I mean we don't call it an insect but the
תורה Torah really calls them all שרץ המים sheretz hamayim so first
of all there's a question if the תורה Torah distinguishes. But second
of all here it's not just things that grow naturally in the
water because actually the prohibition by the land is שרץ הארץ sheretz
ha'aretz so if it hasn't crawled on the ground it's just been
in the fruit or the vegetable that's where it grew because the
seeds were laid that's might not be a problem but here it
is a שרץ המים. sheretz hamayim. Nevertheless it is somewhat similar because
what we're saying is that things that grew in standing water and
were never separated from it are never forbidden and we're going to
see later that when they are separated from the water then they
actually do become forbidden similar to when the bug gets separated from
the fruit. So on the one hand you could sort of say
oh so in theory if there was a crab in standing water
it wouldn't be a problem but it seems that the גמרא's Gemara
emphasis is much more about sort of like the types of small
little insects that are found in it and somewhat following this pattern
about about the שרץ הארץ sheretz ha'aretz because we'll see later a
distinction between whether they were originally there or they separated at one
moment but those but nevertheless the insects that grew in the oceans
are a problem and one could imagine that if it originally grew
in the ocean and now found its way through underground water or
whatever into this well or something it also is a problem. It's
only if it originally grew there. One final thing to think about
before we turn to the גמרא Gemara is that the גמרא Gemara
also you know I've tried to sort of like gloss over the
difference between the גמרא's Gemara science and our science because it really
is some things can grow originally in a certain location if that's
where the eggs were laid. So you know certain you know insects
can grow in the fruit with never having been on the ground
because if the eggs were laid you know at the seed or
something inside the fruit or if the eggs were laid in the
water standing water then the insects can grow even if they you
know originally there. Nevertheless we are going to see later that the
גמרא Gemara assumes that a lot of these things actually grow from
the material in which they are appearing that the insects grow from
the water you know not that the eggs were laid and that
will play a a little bit of a role later on. So
those are the issues that we are going to be seeing. Yes
every fruit has insects. Every fruit has strawberries yeah. Yeah well that's
the idea of all checking things for bugs absolutely. Absolutely. You have
to wash it. Yeah but this is if you found a bug
inside that never was exposed and if you didn't wash it is
it still okay? And the way you know that is you don't
see any opening on the outside right? You don't see any and
that's exactly right and we're going to talk about that later. One
thing I don't understand let's say a cave. The water I mean
obviously has to have some bigger subterranean source so if it bubbles
up from wherever it is that's still considered like a cave? What's
not considered running water right? Because there's also... Exactly. That's what we
pointed out yesterday, that actually what the תורה Torah would call מים
חיים, mayim chayim, we normally think about מים חיים, mayim chayim, I
always thought about מים חיים, mayim chayim, it's funny where we get
our original images from, when I was a kid I watched Yogi
Bear and Yellowstone Park and they always had like one of these
spurting geysers out, so I always sort of thought about that as
מים חיים, mayim chayim, but really מים חיים mayim chayim just means
that it is coming from the ground and it's not rainwater and
well water, which comes from an underground spring, is actually מים חיים,
mayim chayim, but it is not what we're talking about here. Here
we're talking about running water. Okay, so it grows in still standing
water it's okay, if it grows in even if it's natural, if
it grows in running water it's not good. So let's now turn
to the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so we're on ס"ו Samech Vav עמוד
ב' Amud Bet. and it says and we are now and we
learned and we are turning to where it says אימא, Eima, six
lines from the bottom. I think- one minute, hold on. No, no,
I'm sorry, we're not there. Okay, okay, okay, okay. Hang on to
somewhere like most of the- אימא, Eima, אימא, Eima, it's the word
אימא, Eima, the line starts with the word לאכל Le'echol and it
is eleven lines from the bottom. Okay, yes, what? It says אימא
בכלים. Eima Bakeilim. So the גמרא Gemara says since the תורה Torah
says this you may eat from that that's in the waters and
the oceans and the rivers, it says, "Oh, only in the oceans
and the rivers it needs סימנים, simanim. but if it's in כלים,
keilim, if it grows in vessels, it doesn't even need these סימנים,
simanim, it's kosher even without these סימנים." simanim, So the גמרא Gemara
says, "One minute, maybe I could read the verse another way. אימא,
Eima, why don't I say בכלים אף אגב דאית ליה לא תאכל.
Bakeilim af agav de'is lei lo tachal. Maybe you should read the
verse like this, that right, more מחמיר. machmir. If it's in the
oceans and the rivers, then you may eat it with these סימנים.
simanim. But something that's just in כלים, keilim, you can't eat it
regardless. Okay, so maybe it's only allowing it in oceans and rivers.
It's more מחמיר machmir in oceans and rivers, it's more מקל meikel
in oceans and rivers." So the גמרא Gemara says, "לא סלקא דעתך,
Lo salka daatach, that doesn't make sense. דכתיב Dechsiv because the verse
says וכל אשר אין לו, vechol asher ein lo, the same way
it frames it in the positive it frames it in the negative.
Anything that doesn't have סנפיר וקשקשת, snapir vekaskeset, fins and scales, בימים
ובנחלים מכל שרץ המים. bayamim uvanchalim mikol sheretz hamayim. So in the
oceans and the rivers from all those that creep in the ocean,
so it says בימים ובנחלים bayamim uvanchalim when it's in the oceans
and rivers דלית ליה deleis lei and it doesn't have the right
סימנים, simanim. then לא תאכל, lo tachal, that's when you may not
eat it.
הא בכלים, Ha bakeilim, but if it's in vessels, אף אגב
דלית ליה אכול
af
agav
deleis lei echol
even without those סימנים simanim, eat."
So it's saying, "Okay, but we have a negative verse that says
if it's
in oceans and rivers
and it doesn't have סימנים simanim you might not eat. You may
not eat." So the only thing you can't eat
is something in oceans and rivers lacking these סימנים.
simanim But in other
waters you may always eat regardless.
Okay, so we're basically saying of course the question still is
why focus on the prohibiting verse rather than the permitting verse, but
be that as it may we're saying we have a prohibiting verse
and we're going to take that to be what is indicative and
that
says that the only thing that's prohibited is lacking those סימנים simanim.
in oceans and rivers. But in other waters it's always okay. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says, "ואימא, V'eima, why don't I say ואימא
במים כלל, V'eima bamayim klal, in water is a כלל, klal, general
statement, right, any waters. בימים ובנחלים פרט. Bayamim uvanchalim prat. So first
it says you may not eat from all the things in the
water, so waters any waters. Then it says oceans and rivers, that's
a specific. כלל ופרט אין בכלל אלא מה שבפרט. Klal uprat ein
baklal ela mah shebaprat. General and specific, we only have what's in
the specific. ימים ונחלים אין נצים וחריצים לא. Yamim venachalim in nitzim
vecharitzim lo. So then we wouldn't include all running water. Let's say
only exactly what's mentioned in the תורה, Torah, only oceans and rivers.
So things that are more ditches and gullies- well right, no, but
those aren't running actually. I mean how do they translate there חריצים
charitzim and נצים? nitzim? Can I see just how the English translates
this? Sorry bro. Gutters and trenches. That's pretty close to what I
said. Okay, so no, so maybe other things that are running water
but
are not oceans and rivers,
streams, whatever, right, maybe those would be okay? Right, so how come
you say anything that's running water is a problem? Maybe we should
say the תורה Torah is exact.
The only thing where there's an issue with the סימנים simanim is
only oceans and rivers."
Well that's what we're going to have to say. There isn't actually.
We're going to see. Micha, let's read it, okay. The כלל klal
after it, it's a כלל klal beforehand. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says כלל ופרט אין במים אלא מה שבפרט,
klal
uprat
ein bamayim ela mah shebaprat, only oceans and rivers. So the גמרא
Gemara says ימים ונחלים אין נצים וחריצים לא, yamim venachalim in nitzim
vecharitzim lo, only oceans and rivers not the streams and you know
ravines or whatever that have water in it. So the גמרא Gemara
says, "במים חזר וכלל." Bamayim chazar vechalal. No, it says another במים
bamayim like Micha said, so it's a כלל פרט וכלל klal prat
ukhlal that lets us generalize a little bit and say anything like
oceans and rivers meaning anything with running water. But the גמרא Gemara
says, "One minute, הני תרי כללי דסמכי אהדדי. Hani trei klalei de'samkhi
a'hadadi. These are not- these two כללים klalim come one right after
the other. It's not כלל פרט וכלל, klal prat ukhlal, it's כלל
כלל ופרט." klal klal uprat. Now I don't- forgot to bring a
חומש Chumash here with me. Didn't- they don't quote the פסוק pasuk
in the... The basic let me see if I can pull it
up. The basic פסוק passuk is את זה תאכלו מכל אשר במים.
Et zeh tochlu mikol asher bamayim. Here I'll try to do it.
את זה תאכלו מכל אשר במים כל אשר לו סנפיר וקשקשת במים
בימים ובנחלים אותם תאכלו. Et zeh tochlu mikol asher bamayim kol asher
lo snapir ve'kaskeset bamayim bayamim uvanachalim otam tochlu. So it says במים,
bamayim, במים, bamayim, and then בימים ובנחלים. bayamim uvanachalim. So it has
the general, the general and then the specific. It doesn't go general,
specific, general, which is what we normally need to make our כלל
פרט וכלל klal prat u'klal דרשה. drasha. But then for those that
don't have סנפיר וקשקשת? snapir ve'kaskeset? No, it's the same problem actually,
same problem. It is, trust me Michael. Yeah, the גמרא Gemara didn't
quote the end of the פסוק passuk if you noticed, conveniently, because,
take a look, look, trust me Michael, I checked. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says, so אמר רבינא, Amar Ravina, so רבינא Ravina says
כי דאמרי במערבא, ke'd'amrei be'ma'arava, like they say in the west, in
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, כל מקום שאתה מוצא שני כללות הסמוכים זה
לזה, kol makom she'atah motzei shnei klalot hasmuchim zeh la-zeh, if you
ever have this phenomenon of two כללות, klalot, כלל כלל ופרט, klal
klal u'prat, and not כלל פרט וכלל, klal prat u'klal, AAB, not
ABA, what can you do? Don't worry about it! הטל פרט ביניהם
ודונהו בכלל ופרט וכלל. Hatel prat beineihem ve'dunehu be'klal u'prat u'klal. Okay,
so rearrange the order if you have AAB, put the B in
the middle of the two A's and make it an ABA and
you can do your כלל פרט וכלל klal prat u'klal דרשה drasha
even if you have this type of an order. This means that
you might you might suspect that that's maybe more רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael school than רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva school. Actually interestingly we're going
to revisit רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael in a minute. So therefore we
reorder it. במים Bamayim כלל, klal, water is general, בימים ובנחלים bayamim
uvanachalim פרט, prat, oceans and rivers specific, במים bamayim and then the
other במים mayim which was actually said before and now we're putting
it afterwards, חזר וכלל, chazar ve'klal, another general statement, כלל ופרט וכלל
אי אתה דן אלא כעין הפרט, klal u'prat u'klal ee atah dan
ela ke'ein haprat, so you make it like the specific. מה פרט
מפורש מים נובעים, Mah prat meforash mayim nov'im, the same way the
specific is flowing water, אף כל מים נובעים. af kol mayim nov'im.
So any any flowing water it needs to have fish need these
כשר non-kosher סימנים, simanim fish or water creatures need these סימנים. simanim.
But in standing water, if you have things that grow in standing
water, those actually are כשר kosher regardless. Okay, and again of course
there's a very practical implication as the גמרא Gemara said before, which
is the basic point that you can just drink well water and
you don't have to worry about all the insects. What are you
supposed to do if you want to drink well water and that's
where most people were on the journeys, they needed to drink their
well water? So it says don't worry, it's standing water, you don't
have to worry about the little insects that are in it. But
what about our water, like our tap water? Well our tap water
comes from a river but then we have pipes to bring it.
I mean otherwise if not for the pipes it would just be
sitting there, wouldn't it? No, but does it come from a standing
reservoir, does it come from any running water, the water that feeds
our faucet? That's true. I thought it comes from I don't know,
but it
might it might differ by location.
Ours comes from upstate. I thought it comes from the Croton, it's
hard for me to imagine that it doesn't come from any running
water, the New York tap water is. Really? It does come from
all standing water? I wonder why that didn't get raised then in
the whole copepod issue. I'll look into it. I don't know, I
don't know, that's a very interesting point. If if it is true
that all of our water comes from like standing water, from underground
aquifers, non-flowing water, then it should have been raised. Well a lot
of our drinking water comes from the Croton Reservoir. Reservoir, that's what
he said, from the New York Reservoir. And that is standing water?
Over here, but in other places... Aha. Really? I think it feeds
into the city. Yeah of course it does, I mean it just
it's just... But if it feeds in from the Catskills underground like
by rivers, right? Oh, rivers and streams and whatever. Okay so that's
the difference. Anyway so I want to just quote you for example
the הרא"ש Rosh when he's bringing this down להלכה, l'halacha, says basically
just repeats the practical relevance of it, and he says let me
just read it... yeah he just says, so he quotes the גמרא
Gemara about you can drink from the בורות ושיחין, borot ve'shichin, you
can drink from the wells. ואינו חושש שמא יזדמן לתוך פיו תולעים
שבמים. Ve'eino choshesh shema yizdamen l'toch piv tola'im shebamayim.
You don't have to be concerned whether
you're going to get some type of worms that grow in the
water or we would probably say bugs or insects in the water.
You don't have to worry about it. You can just drink straight
from the wells. Okay, so that's what we do. Only with running
water is this a problem. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says okay,
אף כל מים נובעים. af kol mayim nov'im. מאי רביי? Mai ribei?
Now the גמרא Gemara is going to spend the next עמוד amud
probably just pretty much rehashing this דרשה drasha and clarifying it. So
let's take a look. מאי רביי, Mai ribei, what does it include,
the כלל? klal? חריצים ונעיצים לאיסורא. Charitzim u'ne'itzim le'issura. It's including even
like ditches and valleys or whatever, channels that are prohibited, even though
because it's running water. ומאי מיעט, U'mai mi'et, what's excluded from being
the problem? Not only vessels but בורות שיחין ומערות, borot shichin u'mearot,
even things that are like in nature, not only like artificial like
vessels, but they're just standing water, like cisterns, wells and whatever, and
I guess maybe that מערות mearot is maybe cave wells, never occurred
to me. להיתירא, Le'heira, those are permitted. So that's the dividing line
between running water and non-running water. So the גמרא Gemara says why
did that where you divide the line? ואימא, Ve'eima, why don't you
say מה פרט מפורש מים גדלים על גבי קרקע אף כל מים
גדלים על גבי קרקע, mah prat meforash mayim gedelim al gabei karka
af kol mayim gedelim al gabei karka, excuse me, מה פרט מפורש
מים גדלים על גבי קרקע אף כל מים גדלים על גבי קרקע,
mah prat meforash mayim gedelim al gabei karka af kol mayim gedelim
al gabei karka, maybe make the difference between any natural water as
opposed to in a vessel, right? So if it's anything that grows
in its natural state is a problem. Hard to, again, for us
we'd have to say that it formed because the eggs were in
the vessel when it was removed and then they just hatched when
it was inside. Okay, so maybe the difference, the line is not
running versus non-running, but natural versus in its natural in situ rather
than actually having been in a vessel. So the גמרא Gemara says,
ומאי רבי אפילו בורות שיחין ומערות לאיסורני, u'mai rabi afilu borot shichin
u'mearot l'issurani, therefore even wells and cisterns and caves are going to
be a problem. So the גמרא Gemara says, ומה מיעט, u'mah mi'et,
what's excluded? What is not a problem? מיעט בכלים, mi'et b'keilim, only
if it occurs in a vessel, and presumably it originates in a
vessel. So the גמרא Gemara says it would be a major problem
then anybody wants to drink from a well.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אם כן, im kein,
if that's true, תאכלו מאי
אהני ליה.
tochlu mai
ahani lei.
Remember this whole discussion started because it said, why did the verse
have to
say both don't eat and eat? So the first answer was, oh,
it's telling us to tell you there's
a
negative
prohibition and a
positive מצוה mitzvah that
you would transgress if you ate non-kosher fish or non-kosher seafood creatures.
So then it says, oh, but it says you may eat it
or you shall eat it twice. What's the second תאכלו tochlu doing?
So
the second תאכלו tochlu
is telling you that you can eat some of these insects and
things that don't have the סימנים simanim when they grow in standing
water.
So the גמרא Gemara is
saying that's exactly how it's functioning. Justify the כלל ופרט וכלל, klal
u'prat u'klal, I might have made the, I might have abstracted from
oceans and rivers very generally and I might have said any natural
water is a problem.
And the only thing I would have allowed is
insects to grow in כלים. keilim. Since it says מזה תאכלו אשר
במים, mizeh tochlu asher bamayim, this
is what you shall eat, מכל אשר במים mikol asher bamayim
from anything in the
water, the emphasis is, oh, there's
a lot of things you can eat that
grow in, that come in water, even not limited to the next
thing.
So that extra expanding thing of
things you can eat is coming to say don't just allow the
insects that grow in the vessels, allow any insects that grow even
in standing water, even in the wells and the cisterns. So again,
what we do is we're abstracting, you need to have the kosher
סימנים simanim from the oceans and the rivers. So
how far do you abstract? You say anything like them running water,
or anything like them natural water? So the גמרא Gemara says the
reason we don't go all the way and are more strict and
say anything like them natural water, and the reason we limit it
to running water and we draw the line there, is because we
have another verse telling us more things are permissible. And the other
verse is תאכלו כל אשר במים, tochlu kol asher bamayim, that you
may eat things that are in the water. אותם תאכלו, otam tochlu,
no, not אותם תאכלו, otam tochlu, that's the עשה. asei. תאכלו כל
אשר במים tochlu kol asher bamayim is you may eat things that
are in the water. We need to put those together, you get
what I'm saying? Right. Okay. אותם תאכלו otam tochlu is the עשה
asei and תאכלו אשר במים tochlu asher bamayim is the one that
we're focusing on. Okay, so so that's one דרשה, drasha, which is
the כלל ופרט. klal u'prat. Now we're basically going to say almost
the exact same thing or almost the exact same thing based on
the principle of ריבוי ומיעוט ribbuy u'mi'ut and not כלל ופרט וכלל.
klal u'prat u'klal. So let's take a look. Okay, תנא דבי רבי
ישמעאל תנא, tana d'bei Rabbi Yishmael tana, the house of Rabbi Yishmael
they taught, במים במים שתי פעמים, bamayim bamayim shtei pe'amim, it says
במים bamayim twice, אין זה כלל ופרט אלא ריבוי ומיעוט. ein zeh
klal u'prat ella ribbuy u'mi'ut. So that's the ריבוי ומיעוט ribbuy u'mi'ut
method. Now, it sounds like he would say normally I wouldn't say
ריבוי ומיעוט, ribbuy u'mi'ut, but because it says it not ABA but
AAB, that signals to me ריבוי ומיעוט. ribbuy u'mi'ut. What's the difference?
The difference here is the following. First of all, I'll just tell
you the bottom-line difference and then I'll tell you sort of maybe
a little bit how it gets there. The difference is like this:
כלל ופרט וכלל, klal u'prat u'klal, right, when you have general-specific-general, that
approach says anything similar to the פרט, prat, anything similar to B.
Okay, that's the שיטה shita of כלל ופרט וכלל. klal u'prat u'klal.
ריבוי ומיעוט או ריבוי, ribbuy u'mi'ut o ribbuy, ABA, says no, no,
no, since you have two כללים, klalim, ABA, it's really everything is
included except the thing that is the most dissimilar from B. Okay?
So B is only coming to exclude things that are extremely dissimilar
to it, but it doesn't have to be that similar to B.
It just has to be not completely dissimilar. A classic example is
by the מנורה. Menorah. It says, what does it say by מנורה?
Menorah? It says וזה אשר תעשה את המנורה, v'zeh asher ta'aseh et
hamenorah, so כלל, klal, so whatever make it, I guess out of
everything. זהב, zahav, then it says gold, and then it says מקשה
תעשה את המנורה, miksha ta'aseh et hamenorah, make it out of anything.
כלל ופרט וכלל. klal u'prat u'klal. So if you say כלל ופרט
וכלל, klal u'prat u'klal, you'll say it has to be like gold,
it has to be metal, not even precious metals, metals. If you
say ריבוי ומיעוט וריבוי, ribbuy u'mi'ut u'ribbuy, you say anything unless something
that is the most dissimilar from gold. What's the most dissimilar from
gold? Pottery. That's considered like the cheapest material, the most fragile material.
Anything else? You could even make it out of wood, that would
be okay. So that was a question whether they originally in the
time of the חשמונאים Chashmonaim made the מנורה Menorah out of wood
or not. Okay, anyway, so that's the difference. Now, how do you
get to that difference? Why does one... so רש"י Rashi explains it
as the following, because it starts not at the ABA stage, the
difference starts at the AB stage. כלל ופרט klal u'prat says that
what I have is a general and a specific. So if I
have a general and a specific, I say, you know, oh, go
get me some supper, anything really, you know, fish. So or fish
and meat. So I want fish and meat—I made a general statement,
but in the end I mean specific. So the כלל ופרט Klal
U-Prat says that when you're at the AB stage, all you have
is the פרט. Prat. So therefore, only when you get the final
A stage, where I say, "You know, oh, get me anything for
dinner. You know, fish, meat, fish, really anything." So then you'll say,
"Oh, okay, so chicken also." Okay, so at the AB stage, I
was just the things I was saying, I was just the פרט.
Prat. Then if I made another general statement, I expand the פרט
Prat a little bit. And therefore it's anything like the פרט. Prat.
Okay, however, if I am doing ריבוי ומיעוט, Ribuy U-Miyut, the words
mean something different. The words mean from the very outset, I'm not
saying that this is specific, it's a פרט, Prat, I'm saying it's
limiting. Already I'm talking in abstractions. So when I say everything, I
mean everything. When I say AB, everything, like fish and meat, I'm
not giving those as specific examples. I'm just giving it as a
מיעוט, Miyut, as an abstract limiting. So already at the AB stage,
I'm already at anything like B. Meaning by abstract—meaning, if I'm saying,
you know, fish or meat, fish or meat, so if I'm כלל
ופרט, Klal U-Prat, I mean exactly fish and meat, okay? If I'm
ריבוי ומיעוט, Ribuy U-Miyut, I'm looking at those as—even at the AB
stage, I'm looking at those as examples, you know, not as specific.
So they're examples. I mean not really everything, I mean something like
fish and meat, but not vegetables, right? Not a salad, exactly. So
when I'm already at the B stage, I'm already at anything like
B. I'm not giving you specifics, I'm giving you examples. So then
the כלל ופרט וכלל, Klal U-Prat U-Klal, the final כלל Klal expands
it even more, and not כלל, Klal, the final ריבוי Ribuy expands
it even more and really says, "Really, you can get anything unless
it's the thing the most different from this from—you know, from this."
I don't know what that would be. You can get me fake
meat, but don't get—I don't know, whatever. Okay. So anyway, that's the
difference. The difference is not only what you do at the ABA
stage, but what you do at the AB stage. The כלל ופרט
Klal U-Prat says that at the AB, you only have B, so
by the time you get to the final A, it's anything like
B. The ריבוי ומיעוט Ribuy U-Miyut says that at AB, you already
have anything like B, so by the time you get to A,
you're including everything except things that are the most disliked. Now here
it sounds that רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael in general would be a
כלל ופרט Klal U-Prat man. Normally you find people that have consistent
approaches. "I'm always going to explain it this way" or "always the
other way." The language here of רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael sounds like
in general he'd be a כלל ופרט Klal U-Prat man, but because
it emphasized the כלל Klal doubly, it went AA B, it doubly
emphasized the כלל Klal right at the outset, that tells you to
take a more expansive דרשה drasha and do it more as a
ריבוי ומיעוט Ribuy U-Miyut and not as a כלל ופרט. Klal U-Prat.
Exactly, that's the way it sounds like from רבי ישמעאל. Rebbi Yishmael.
So now let's take a look. In the end, it's all going
to boil down to the same thing. Okay, but that was a
fun opportunity to talk about those different hermeneutic approaches. So, דבי רבי
ישמעאל תנא במים במים שתי פעמים אין זה כלל ופרט אלא ריבוי
ומיעוט.
Debei Rebbi Yishmael tanna, bamayim
bamayim
shtei pe'amim, ein zeh klal u-prat ela ribuy u-miyut. It's the ריבוי
ומיעוט Ribuy U-Miyut which tends to be the more expansive דרשה. drasha.
במים Bamayim ריבוי. ribuy. So במים bamayim is an inclusive. בימים ובנחלים,
Bayamim u-venechalim, oceans and rivers, מיעוט, miyut, that's already limiting. Okay. במים
Bamayim חזר וריבה. chazar ve-ribah. It goes and includes again. ריבוי ומיעוט
וריבוי. Ribuy u-miyut ve-ribuy. So inclusive, limiting, and inclusive. ריבה הכל. ribah
hakol. It includes everything or almost everything. מאי ריבה? mai ribei? What
is it including? חריצין ונעיצין ואיסורא. charitzin u-ne'itzin ve-issura. Even like these
gullies and ditches are forbidden. Right, that's included in the oceans and
rivers. ומאי מיעט? u-mai mi'et? What's excluded? בור שיחין ומערות להתירא. bor
shichin u-me'arot le-heteira. So that the wells and the cisterns, those are
going to be permissible. So the upshot was, we had this whole
big thing about a difference between כלל ופרט וכלל klal u-prat u-klal
and ריבוי ומיעוט וריבוי, ribuy u-miyut ve-ribuy, and he winds up saying
the exact same thing. Okay, so תוספות, Tosafot, that's within רש"י, Rashi,
and he has that problem and whatever, we'll see how he deals
with it in a minute, but תוספות Tosafot actually says there is
a difference. This approach, which is more inclusive, and here inclusive means
strict because it's including in what's אסור, assur, would actually include gullies
and ditches, even standing water. Okay, as opposed to before we emphasized
flowing water was the point, here we would say gullies and ditches
even if it's standing water are going to be a problem. So
תוספות Tosafot tries to make this a little bit more inclusive and
a little bit stricter, or else what's the whole point about making
a different דרשה? drasha? But רש"י Rashi sees them as saying the
exact same thing. Okay, it's just we got to it through the
ריבוי ומיעוט. ribuy u-miyut. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, so
the גמרא Gemara says: אימא, eima, one minute, why do I wind
up with that conclusion? אימא, eima, why don't I say: מאי ריבה,
mai ribah, what is it including? בור שיחין ומערות לאיסורא. bor shichin
u-me'arot le-issura. Maybe actually because you're doing a ריבוי ומיעוט דרשה, ribui
u'miut drasha, you should be much broader, and in here this would
mean much more strict. So a lot of things should be included
in the idea of oceans and rivers, and let it even include
wells and cisterns, because that's also natural water, and those are forbidden.
ומאי מיעט u-mai mi'et and the only... Something that would be excluded
is the thing most unlike wells oceans and rivers, which is what,
מי כלים? mei keilim? So this actually would make a lot of
sense, right, if you're doing a ריבוי ומיעוט ribuy u-miyut דרשה, drasha,
then you're going to say everything even slightly similar to oceans and
rivers. So what is that? All all natural water. The only thing
that's the most dissimilar is water in vessels. So if you're a
ריבוי ומיעוט, ribui u'miut, you should really only allow this היתר heter
to apply to water in vessels. So the גמרא Gemara says once
again like I said before, no. אם כן תאכלו מאי אהני ליה.
im ken tochlu mai ahani lei. What good is the verse that
says this you may eat from anything in the water? So you're
right. Based on ריבוי ומיעוט ribui u'miut you really should have forbidden
even insects that grow in the in the wells. But because because
you would have been much more you would have included everything somewhat
similar to oceans and rivers. But because the other verse says this
you may eat from everything in the water, which is saying more
things that you can eat, we say draw the line somewhere else.
Say that even wells and cisterns, anything standing water, if insects grow
in it, it's not a problem. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says
ואיפוך אנא, ve'ipoch ana, why don't I reverse it? Why don't I
forbid the ditches, I mean allow the ditches and forbid the wells?
What's the logic here? We know what the logic is, but the
גמרא Gemara is just articulating it. כדתני מתיא, kedetani Matya, because we
as מתיא Matya teaches. Interesting name, we don't see that too much.
דתני מתיא detani Matya or like מתתיהו Mattityahu without the ו. vav.
מתיא Matya taught, בר יהודה, bar Yehuda, מאי ראית לרבות בורות שיחין
ומערות לטהרה, mai raita lerabot borot shichin ume'arot letahara, why is it
that the wells and the cisterns are permissible if insects grow in
them, water insects, ולהוציא חריצין ונעיצין לאיסורא, ulehotzi charitzin vene'itzin leisura, and
the ditches and the you know whatever they are, trenches or whatever,
those types of things are forbidden? מרבה אני בורות שיחין ומערות שעצורים
ככלים. marbe ani borot shichin ume'arot she'atzurim kekeilim. I include the wells
etc. where the water is gathered and standing like in vessels. So
that's the dissimilar enough from oceans and rivers, and if insects and
water creatures grow in there, it's okay. ומוציא אני חריצין ונעיצין שאין
עצורים ככלים umotzi ani charitzin vene'itzin she'ein atzurim kekeilim and I exclude
the ditches and the
trenches where water runs through, שאין עצורים ככלים
she'ein atzurim kekeilim because the water there is not gathered but the
water actually runs. Okay, so that's what we've always assumed, but here
it just spells it out. Okay. Now that is the end of
that. So whether it's כלל ופרט וכלל klal u'prat u'klal or ריבוי
ומיעוט, ribui u'miut, we wind up because we have this extra verse
of תאכלו כל אשר במים, tochlu kol asher bamayim, we know to
draw the line in a slightly more permissive way. So we say
not only vessels, but even anything like standing water, even natural like
wells, the insects that grow in the water creatures that grow are
not a problem. Now if you remember yesterday, there was a very
obscure line, not obscure, whatever, hard to interpret line which said, oh,
since the תורה Torah said in an explicit case that you can
eat things that are in standing water, so it has to also
tell you, you know, that even in the not only in the
מפורש meforash case, the explicit case, but even in the סתום, satum,
even in the non-explicit case, it also is you draw a line
between standing water and non-standing water. So what's explicit and what's not
explicit? So the גמרא Gemara is going to say for whatever reason,
and I really wish I had brought a תנ"ך Tanakh with me,
that explicit is the verse that says what you may eat, and
implicit, סתום, satum, is the verse that says what you may not
eat. Okay, because since we're trying to allow things, so to have
to learn it out from a verse that says this is what
you may eat is like it said explicitly in that verse to
allow it. If you only learn it out from the verse that
says you may not eat and you can infer that, oh, but
things that grow in standing water are okay, that's considered to be
implicitly stated. So let's take a look. I really need a... You
going to get one? Okay. Thank you, bud. Okay. So now it's
not there. Okay, I will just wait a second. Can you just
try to tilt that a tiny bit this way, the whole stand?
I want to get the... Yeah. If you guys... the camera. Oh,
perfect. Okay. Try to get a little more centered. All right, anyway,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. So האי סתום
והאי מפורש. hai satum vehai meforash. Which of the verse which is
not explicit, implicit, and what is explicit? So פליגי בה רב אחא
ורבינא. pligi bah Rav Acha veRavina. They debated. חד אמר יש לו
מפורש ואין לו סתום. chad amar yesh lo meforash ve'ein lo satum.
This verse about the insects that grow in the water, it's in
the it has an explicit verse about it but not an implicit.
Again, the explicit verse is the verse that says what you may
eat, the implicit verse is the verse that says what you may
not eat because here we're coming to allow things. Okay. וחד אמר
אין לו מפורש ויש לו סתום. vechad amar ein lo meforash veyesh
lo satum. It doesn't have an explicit verse but it is in
the implicit verse. Okay, and now now we're doing the same thing,
right? No, well no, they're saying one of the practically the same.
But one of the verses that talks about whether you can eat
these types of insects, is it more in the verse that's explicit
or more in the verse that is implicit? Meaning more in the
verse that permits, is that where we derive it from, or more
in the verse that forbids? So let me read you the two
verses and then we and then we'll see what the גמרא Gemara
does with them. These are the מפורש meforash and סתום. satum. Land
animals, here we go. Okay, so it says like this: ואת זה
תאכלו מכל אשר במים, V'et zeh tokhlu mikol asher bamayim, this is
what you may eat which is in the water, כל אשר לו
סנפיר וקשקשת במים בימים ובנחלים אתם תאכלו, kol asher lo snapir ve'kaskeset
bamayim bayamim uvanechalim otam tokhlu, anything that has, you know, the fins
and scales, whatever, and it mentions במים ובנחלים. bamayim uvanechalim. So if
we're going to say, oh, only במים ובנחלים bamayim uvanechalim is it
an issue and not in other standing water, that sounds, you know,
a reasonable דרשה drasha to say it's somewhat explicit in that verse,
explicit at least through rabbinic hermeneutic eyes. Okay, now וכל אשר אין
לו, vekhol asher ein lo, here's why the next verse might be
seen as less clearly communicating that idea, because it says like this:
וכל אשר אין לו סנפיר וקשקשת בימים ובנחלים מכל שרץ המים ומכל
נפש החיה אשר במים שקץ הם לכם. vekhol asher ein lo snapir
ve'kaskeset bayamim uvanechalim mikol sheretz hamayim umikol nefesh hachayah asher bamayim sheketz
hem lachem. So notice that that verse which says this is an
abomination to you, these things that don't have these characteristics in the
oceans and the rivers, so it mentioned it needed the lack of
characteristics was a problem, mentioned oceans and rivers, but notice it did
not say don't eat it. All that first verse said was it
is an abomination. Only the next verse says ושקץ יהיו לכם, vesheketz
yihyu lachem, they are an abomination, מבשרם לא תאכלו, mibsaram lo tokhlu,
don't eat from their flesh, ואת נבלתם תשקצו. ve'et nivaltam tishaktzu. So
the reason to say it's less in this verse is because when
this verse finally gets around to saying don't eat, it's not in
the context of the qualifier of oceans and rivers. That was in
the previous verse. So obviously the verses are connected, but it's a
little less clear in this verse because when it says don't eat
it's no longer in the context of oceans and rivers. But it
only says it once, right? As opposed to תאכלו tokhlu תאכלו, tokhlu,
or אתם תאכלו? otam tokhlu? Right, exactly, that's why. So let's take
a look what גמרא Gemara says. Okay. מאי טעמא דמאן דאמר יש
לו מפורש, Mai ta'ama deman de'amar yesh lo meforash, what is the
reason of the one that says that this is in the explicit
verse, meaning it's in the verse of eating, אמר לך מניה הוא
דקמישתרו כלים, amar lekha mineih hu dekamishtaru kelim, from that verse we
implicitly permit vessels, right? Because it says this you may eat from
things in oceans and rivers, so implicitly vessels and standing water are
different, and therefore that's why that we learn it out from that
verse and that's why it's in that verse. Okay. מאי טעמא דמאן
דאמר אין לו מפורש, Mai ta'ama deman de'amar ein lo meforash, and
so maybe this will become clearer what the issue is about, what's
the reason of the one that says that no, that verse about
what you may eat is not explicitly communicating that idea, we only
get it from the next verse? Because he says דהאי הוא דקמוכח
אהאי, dehai hu dekamokhach ahai, that this one informs that one. Now
which is the this and which is the that? The verse about
not eating informs the verse about eating. Because remember the גמרא Gemara
at the beginning of the דף daf today said, if I only
have the verse about eating, I might have interpreted it more strict,
I might have said from things that are in oceans and rivers
you can eat if they have the סימנים, simanim, from things that
are in standing water you can never eat, the only thing you
can eat is oceans and rivers with the סימנים. simanim. So if
I only had the statement about oceans and rivers in the eating
verse, I would have said that when it's in other waters you
may not eat. It's because the oceans and rivers is in the
you may not eat verse, I say the only thing you may
not eat is oceans and rivers without the סימנים, simanim, but in
other waters you can eat anything. So the verse about not eating
more clearly leads to saying that when it's in standing water it's
permissible. So what it says is this one, the one about not
eating, informs the verse about eating. The one about not, what do
you do with saying standing water is different? Is standing water always
forbidden or standing water always permitted? So that's a clearer, we more
clearly learn out that standing water is always permitted from the verse
about not eating. So therefore the verse about not eating is really
our anchor and the verse about eating is really less clear. So
let me just finish it. דהאי הוא דקמוכח אהאי, Dehai hu dekamokhach
ahai, this one, the not eating, is the one that tells us
what the one about eating is talking about. דאי מהאי, de'ei mehai,
if it was only that one, the one about eating, הוה אמינא,
havah amina, I would have said like we started the דף daf
today, בכלים אף על גב דאית ליה נמי לא תאכלו, bekelim af
al gav de'is lei nami lo tokhlu, if it's in standing water
and vessels, even if it has the סימנים, simanim, you can't eat.
So one says it's clearer in the first verse because that's where
it explicitly is in the context of what you may eat, whereas
in the second verse it doesn't really talk about not eating till
it gets to a later thing. That's how רש''י Rashi explains, not
even in the גמרא. Gemara. But that's why he focuses the first
verse is the one that we say is where it's clearly communicated.
And the other says no, because if I just had the first
verse I would have been even stricter by vessels. The way I
know to be more lenient by vessels is by the second verse,
so that's what I'm going to say is the anchor and then
it just
informs the first verse.
In the end, they all agree, it's just a question of which
one are we saying is more explicit than the other. But at
the end of the day, if we say that you've your two
תאכלוs, tokhlu right, then why do you even need the negative verse?
Because you could just said that the תאכלו tokhlu is saying that
you can't be strict to begin with because of the תאכלו, tokhlu,
which means you're coming to be more lenient, in which case you
don't even need...
maybe I would have just said that it's
coming to allow things in standing water with the סימנים, simanim, but
I wouldn't allow them without the סימנים, simanim, right? If I didn't
have the don't eat verse, I wouldn't have, you know, that really
tells me that in standing water everything is okay, yeah. I just
wanted to mention we were talking about the prawn. The Croton Aqueduct,
the Croton Reservoir, okay, yes, which is 30 miles north of the
city. Okay. It was formed by impounding the West Branch and Middle
Branch of the Croton River, which are tributaries of the Muscoot River,
which in turn is a tributary of the Croton River which flows
into the Hudson River. Okay. So it's all moving water that forms
the reservoir. So there goes that. Okay. So now, so good. Now
let's move on. Now the גמרא Gemara turns to be practical. I
mean, it was practical there, but it was a lot of דרשות.
drashos. Now we turn to some bottom line. Okay. אמר רב הונא,
Amar Rav Huna, לא ישפי אינש שיכרא בצביאתא באורתא. Lo Yishpi Inish
Shichra Bitzivyasa Be'orsa. A person should not pour mead, beer, through little
chips of wood. They used that as a filter. They would pour
liquids through chips of wood in order to get out the bugs.
Okay, don't do that at night. Okay, now we're assuming that there
might be bugs that grow in the beer, and we're assuming that
those are going to grow, it's like this case about בקלין, bakalin,
that they will form naturally in the beer. They're not, well they
certainly didn't come from any river or ocean. Okay, but the question
is, you know, this is like, you know, this was all before
they did the whole, you know, experiment about spontaneous generation. So they
probably assumed that they spontaneously generated from the beer. It could be
that, you know, some insect came and laid eggs and then left.
But it could also be that insects just came from outside and
came into the beer. Or also something that was laid on the
leaf of a tree and the leaves were blown and the eggs
fell from... you mean they were in the fruits.
No, no, no, this is beer, so they were making it from
the...
they were squeezing it, they were making it, or they were actually
making it from like dates. Mead, not beer, mead. Mead, you know.
So anyway, so this is an example of the insects that are
in a liquid, water insects, okay? Or it's not exactly clear if
this is treating it about water or land insects because this isn't
like a natural formed body of water. Let's take a look. Don't
pour it through these chips of wood at night. Why? Because at
night you won't see what's happening. דילמא פריש אצביאתא, dilma parish el
am tziyvasa, maybe a bug will separate out above the chips of
wood, right? The filter will be successful. והדר נפל לכסא, v'hadar nafal
lekasah, and then it will go back into the cup. והוי עובר
משום שרץ השורץ על הארץ. v'havei over mishum sheretz hashoretz al ha'aretz.
So if it always grew in the beer, it would never have
been השורץ על הארץ. hashoretz al ha'aretz. But as soon as it
separates from the beer and is no longer in the liquid where
it naturally grew but is on the ground, you know, or not
on the ground but at least on the chips of wood, that's
considered שרץ על הארץ shoretz al ha'aretz and then falls back. Why
is that only problematic at night? Because רש"י Rashi says if it
was the day and you saw that happening, then you either wouldn't
eat the beer or you would remove it. But if it happens
at night and you didn't see it happen, even if you see
the insect in the beer, mead I should say not beer, you're
going to say it's not a problem, it grew there naturally and
it was never שרץ על הארץ, shoretz al ha'aretz, end of story.
Yes, it wouldn't be like a yeast form, beer would be concerning
yeast. Yes, not yeast. This is mead. I misspoke, it's not beer.
Okay. So, I have a question. Let me make sure I understood
this. Like, so this is actually, these wood chips are on the
ground? Let's say I kind of... No, no, no. These wood chips
are you're pouring it... it goes through the wood chips into your
cup underneath. Why is that considered על הארץ al ha'aretz even though
it's... Yeah, because it doesn't have to be על הארץ, al ha'aretz,
it's just not in the water. Exactly, right. But then a bug
can always fall in anything you're... Right, right, but the question is,
so that's another question. What do you assume when you see these
bugs? Do you assume they came from outside? Do you assume they
grew naturally in? It sounds like naturally, generally if they are bugs
that we expect to be that naturally occur in mead, then we'll
assume that's where they hatched and grew, unless there's a reason to
suspect that they might have come separated and fallen back, or unless
they look unlike those types of bugs and then we'll have to
be concerned that they came from elsewhere. It's not the separated, it's
the fact that after they separated they moved around. Well, the question
is, do they actually have to move? We'll get to that later.
It might be maybe just the fact that they existed on the
land without moving. We'll get to that in a minute. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this. אי הכי, I hachi, says the
גמרא, Gemara, במנא נמי דילמא פריש לדפנא דמנא והדר נפל למנא. bemana
nami dilma parish ledapna demana vehadar nafal lemana. The גמרא Gemara says
even if you're not sifting it, by sifting it it's actually more
of a problem because you've possibly separated it out. But the stuff
that naturally grows, הלכתית halachically you don't have to sift it. So
the גמרא Gemara says, but if that's true, if we have this
concern, even if you're just pouring from a pitcher into your cup,
let's be concerned that one of the insects got caught on the
rim of the pitcher and then fell into the cup and therefore
separated and therefore it's a שרץ sheretz problem. So the גמרא Gemara
says no. התם היינו רביתיה. Hasam hainu rivisa. That's where it grows.
Now what does that exactly... it's a hard phrase. What do you
mean it's where it grows? It doesn't grow on the lip of
a pitcher. So it really somewhat means like, well that's sort of
natural that the... that these insects will get caught on the vessel
that they're in and then come back and that's not really called
separate. How separate does something have to be before it's considered separate?
So since these things normally exist in their vessels, a little bit
on the lip and falling back is still considered in the same
environment. But having been sifted out, that's considered already separated and that's
a problem. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, ומנא תימרא, umina temra,
how do I know that this is okay until it separates or...
How do I know that we don't concern ourselves for separate, you
know, if it's within the same vessel, separating and falling back? דתניא,
Detanya, we תנא ברייתא, tana Braisa, מניין לרבות פירש והחזירו ממשמרת ושכב
ושצה מהם ואינו נידמם. Minayin lerabbos paresh vehachiziro mimmishmeres veshachav veshase mehem
veino nidmam. How do you know you can take from wells and
not worry about the bugs that grow in the wells? תלמוד לומר,
Talmud Lomar, תאכלו מכל אשר במים, tochlu mikol asher bamayim, you can
eat what is in the water. So how can you do, so
that's what we just said, how can you drink this well water
with the bugs? ואימא פירש לדפנא והדר נפל נפל. Ve’eima paresh ledafna
vehadar nafal nafal. Maybe the well, the bucket that you lowered into
the water got water, as you're pouring from that bucket into your
cup, some bug got caught on the lip of the bucket and
then went into your cup. So why aren't we concerned about that?
And then it becomes forbidden. So notice here what the גמרא Gemara
is doing. It's not saying, oh, if you had a crab, but
it grew in standing water, it's not a problem. It's sort of
putting this into the context of the problem of insects and bugs.
So it's not just that it grew in the standing water that's
not a problem, it's also that it never left that original setting.
But as soon as it separate, it becomes שרץ השרץ על הארץ.
sheretz hasheretz al ha’aretz. So why aren't we concerned about that by
these bugs in the water? סבר? Savar? No, היינו רביתיה, Hainu ravisai,
because that's the natural growth. If it's in the bucket, it'll catch
to the bucket, it's not considered separated yet. הכא נמי היינו רביתיה,
Hacha nami hainu ravisai, same here. It has to really be, you
know, separated in a more significant way. Okay, אמר ליה רב חסדא
לרב הונא, Amar lei Rav Chisda leRav Huna, רב חסדא Rav Chisda
says to רב הונא, Rav Huna, תניא דמסייע לך, Tanya demisaye lach,
a ברייתא Braisa that supports you. כל השרץ השרץ על הארץ. Kol
hasheretz hasheretz al ha’aretz. So now we're going not to verses about
water, bugs or insects, but about land insects. Any creepy thing on
the ground, לרבות יבחושין שסיננו. lerabbos yavchushin shesinenam. That will include even
these יבחושין, yavchushin, which are some place of like flea or whatever
that רש"י Rashi says that they're often in wine that were sifted
out. So if they're sifted out, then they become a problem once
they separate from their natural habitat where they grew in the wine.
טעמא דסיננו, Taama desinenam, the reason is that they were sifted out.
הא לא סיננו שרי. Ha lo sinenam shari. If you didn't sift
them out, you're okay. And you don't have to worry that it
got caught at the lip of the vessel. So it seems like
the following: it seems like things that grow in things like mead
and wine etc., never actually, again, I don't exactly know from the
גמרא. Gemara. It seems like that would is at this stage a
שרץ השרץ על הארץ, sheretz hasheretz al ha’aretz, but it's not yet
אסור assur because it's not yet שרץ על הארץ. sheretz al ha’aretz.
But if you separated, it is. Things that grow in water is
a שרץ המים sheretz hamayim that's not אסור assur if it grew
in standing water. But if that separated, then that stops being a
שרץ המים sheretz hamayim and becomes a שרץ השרץ על הארץ. sheretz
hasheretz al ha’aretz. Okay, so it's sort of coming at it from
different angles. Okay, אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, says שמואל, Shmuel, קישוא שנתליה
באביה. Kishu she’nisliya be’aviha. So you might remember this, this is what
we started a while ago. He says to be considered grow, you
know, moving on the ground, he's actually quite strict. He says if
you have a gourd or whatever קישוא kishu is, the cucumber, okay,
thank you, that the bugs were formed while it was still attached
to the ground, then even though they never left the cucumber, because
they moved in the cucumber when the cucumber was attached to the
ground, that's considered שרץ על הארץ. sheretz al ha’aretz. אסורה משום שרץ
השרץ על הארץ. Assura mishum sheretz hasheretz al ha’aretz. Now that is
extremely strict. Because without שמואל, Shmuel, you could say anytime you open
up a vegetable or fruit and you find bugs in it, you
consume. Well, if you didn't see a hole from the outside, they
grew on the inside, they weren't שרץ הארץ, sheretz ha'aretz, they're okay,
right? It's only with שמואל Shmuel that says that you have to
worry, did they grow when the thing was attached to the ground
or did they grow when it was separated from the ground? So
שמואל Shmuel is very strict. However they grow, whatever, they're somewhere on,
yeah, but the vines are connected to the ground. Right. So that's
what שמואל Shmuel is saying. Okay, so according to שמואל, Shmuel, if
you find bugs, it's not a problem, it's a much bigger problem
because you have to be concerned about when did they grow, when
it was attached or after detached. So the גמרא Gemara is going
to question whether we rule like שמואל. Shmuel. Let's take a look.
לימא מסייע ליה, Leima mesaye lei, let me try to support you,
this position of שמואל. Shmuel. דתני חדא, Detanya chada, על הארץ, al
ha’aretz, we have one ברייתא Braisa that says only when it creeps
on the ground, להוציא את הזיזין שבעדשין, lehotzi es hazizin sheba’adashin, which
excludes, these are all different types of bugs that are particular to
a specific different types of food, vegetation. So excludes, this means that
the זיזין zizin that grow in the lentils, והיתושין שבכליסין, vehayetushin shebakalisin,
and the flies or fleas that grow in the whatever the כליסין
kalisin are, a type of chickpea, thank you, והתולעת שבתמרים, vehatola’as shebatemarim,
and the worms that grow in the date, ושבגרוגרות, veshebigrogeros, and the
pressed dates. Those are all okay, because they never were שרץ על
הארץ, sheretz al ha’aretz, they grew in the fruit. ותניא אידך, Visanya
idach, we have another ברייתא Braisa that says, כל השרץ השרץ על
הארץ, Kol hasheretz hasheretz al ha’aretz, anything, which is more inclusive, לרבות
תולעת שבעיקרי זיתים, lerabbos tola’as shebe’ikrei zeisim, to say what's forbidden, even
the worm that grows at the, you know, the stem of the
olive, ושבעיקרי גפנים, veshebe’ikrei gefanim, or at the stem of the vines.
So what's the difference? If I thought if it grows in the
fruit it's okay, why is one yes and one no? So the
גמרא Gemara says, מאי לאו, mai lav, is it not that this
is the distinction? אידי ואידי בפירי, Idi ve’idi beferei, both of them
grew in the fruit and nevertheless one says it's okay, one says
it's not okay. What's the difference? הא באביה והא דלא באביה. Ha
be’aviha veha dela be’aviha. And this one grew when it was still
attached and therefore it's a problem because it's like it grew, it
was on the ground, and this one grew only after it was
detached. Now how are we supposed to assume that all those cases
about the lentils and the dates or whatever we know that it
grew when it was attached to the ground? I don't know, that's
certainly not פשט. pshat. And the גמרא Gemara actually says no, actually
the פשט pshat is actually exactly against שמואל. Shmuel. So the גמרא
Gemara says no, לא אידי ואידי באביה. Lo, idi v'idi b'aveha. They
could both be talking about that it grew when it was attached.
And here's the difference: לא קשיא הא בפירי הא באילנא גופיה. lo
kashya, ha b'peira ha b'ilana gufeh. One is that it grew inside
the fruit and the other was when it was, when it grew
on the tree. דיקא נמי דקתני תולעת שבעיקרי זיתים ושבעיקרי גפנים. Dika
nami d'katani tolaat she-be-ikrei zeitim u-she-be-ikrei gefanim. When it says what are
the ones that are a problem? It said worms on the stems
of olives and the stems of grapes. So those are a problem
because those are exposed to the outside air. So that's the problem.
שמע מינה. Shma mina. So that we hear. So the simple sense
of these ברייתות braisos is, it doesn't, we are against שמואל. Shmuel.
It doesn't matter if it's attached to the tree as long as
the bug was never exposed to the air. So as long as
the bug was inside the fruit and never came out and was
exposed to the air, it's okay and you don't have to worry
when it grew. The problem about the bugs on the stems of
the olives and the grapes is because those were outside and not,
you know, exposed to the outside air. Now here's a big question:
how do we rule? If you rule like שמואל, Shmuel, you have
to be much stricter because you know, you have to worry when
the thing formed. So if you take a quick look at תוספות,
Tosafos, דיקא נמי דקתני תולעת שבעיקרי זיתים, Dika nami d'katani tolaat she-be-ikrei
zeitim, it says מכאן מדקדק רבינו תם ורבינו נתנאל וריב"א דאין הלכה
כשמואל. mikan medakdek Rabbeinu Tam u-Rabbeinu Nesaneil v-Riva d'ein halacha k'Shmuel. We
don't rule like שמואל. Shmuel. Okay, and then he says one line
later, ובהלכות גדולות ובשאילתות רב אחאי פוסק כשמואל. U-v'Halachos Gedolos u-v'Sheiltos Rav
Achai posek k'Shmuel. It rules like שמואל. Shmuel. Now we've got a
problem. If you're going to rule like שמואל, Shmuel, then if you
find bugs or whatever, it's a much bigger problem because maybe they
got formed while the thing was still attached. And then he says,
if you skip down about eight lines in the narrow lines where
it says מחובר אם בא בעיקרו, mubar im ba b'ikaro, he says
like this, ומיהו אפילו לשמואל, U-mihu afilu l'Shmuel, even according to שמואל,
Shmuel, now you see the practical relevance about this, like we go
crazy about you know, the copepods or whatever, but you see about
how they, you know, they couldn't get their bugs out of a
lot of things and how are they, you know, they couldn't totally
clean their stuff. So how are they going to deal with it?
So a lot of what we've been talking about about saying oh,
bugs that grow naturally in the water aren't a problem, bugs that
grow in whatever isn't a problem. Okay, but once that's a way
of making it tolerable. But of course, if you introduce שמואל, Shmuel,
it's a big issue because then it only allows things that grew
after it was picked. And how do you know? So now תוספות
Tosafos is going to tell you where we have a problem. אין
לאסור, ein le'esor, don't come try to be firm on me and
say we rule like שמואל Shmuel and therefore we're going to forbid
אותם פולים שקורין פוא"ש בלע"ז וחמצי, osam polim she-korin puash b'laaz v'chimtzi,
different types of lentils and peas שקורין שב"יש כשנמצאים בתוכם כגון יחשושין,
she-korin shavish k'she-nimtzaim b'socham k'gon yachshushin, they find there are bugs in
them. ובתחילת תולדותיהן של יחשושין הקליפה משחרת מבחוץ. U-vischilas toldoseihen shel yachshushin
haklipa meshacheres mibachutz. And when they start forming those bugs, the leaves
on the outside get black. Now you, now you think you might
say oh, so as long as you see that they got black
after they were picked, it's okay. But תוספות Tosafos is actually coming
to permit it even when they grew on, in the ground. How
are we going to permit it? So he says וכשמסירים הקליפה נמצאים
היחשושין תחתיה, u-k'she-mesirim haklipa nimtzaim hayachshushin tachteha, when you remove the shell,
you see all of the bugs underneath it. אין לאוסרן, Ein le'osram,
you cannot forbid them even according to שמואל, Shmuel, even though they
grew even though they grew when they were in the ground. ולא
דמי משום השרץ השורץ על הארץ. V'lo dami mishum hasharetz hashoritz al
ha'aretz. Why? כל זמן שלא ריחש. Kol zman shelo richash. Because he
said if they were trapped under the leaf, they were still under
the leaf. They had not yet moved. So he tries to sort
of limit שמואל. Shmuel. שמואל Shmuel says if it's attached on the
ground, but why? Because then it's השרץ על הארץ hashoretz al ha'aretz
if it's moving in the fruit while it's attached to the ground.
But if it was like grown there but has yet to move
and only moves when you open it and never moved on the
ground, then you're okay. So this is a way, but you see
that these approach, that these different permit, allowances are critical to allow
them to e, you know, to survive, to drink well water, to
eat certain types of, you know, vegetables and so on. So if
you rule against שמואל, Shmuel, it's very easy. Anything that was naturally
grew in the thing you're okay. Right, well, that's the question about
also the question is is that when does it consider to be
שרץ על הארץ? shoretz al ha'aretz? If you open it up and
it's still alive and it's moving around, and at that moment is
when it becomes אסור. assur. So it doesn't really help you too
much, right? And a lot of insect, insect infestation happens after it's
well, after after it's picked from the outside, things coming from the
outside. But in theory, yes, so you do, you would not have
to worry about a lot of cases where it naturally grew inside
the thing. The question is going to be what happens when you
open it, if it still moves around, then it becomes forbidden at
that moment. If you swallow it whole, you know, it's different. So
anyway, here you see that whether we rule like שמואל Shmuel or
not has a big implication and תוספות Tosafos is trying to find
a way that even those who rule like שמואל Shmuel can be
lenient based on the idea well, maybe it grew when it was
in the ground but it didn't move, it didn't move. Let's go
back to the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says בעי
רב יוסף, Ba'ei Rav Yosef, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef asked: פירשה
ומתה מהו Pirsha u-mesa mahu? Let's say it separated from the fruit,
okay, but at that moment it died. It never had a chance
to move around. Okay, so that was sort of what we talked
about before about the, you know, about the chips of wood. Okay,
so is it enough that it was out into the outside air
or did it actually have to move in the outside air? What?
Yeah, to some degree it relates to תוספות, Tosfos, how they work
together we can worry about later. מהו? mahu? מקצתה מהו? miktzasah mahu?
Let's say only part of it, let's say you say that is
a problem. What if it's not the whole bug that came out,
only a half of the bug came out? Okay, לאויר העולם מהו?
la'avir ha'olam mahu? Let's say it did not come out on the
ground, this was also a question that you were asking about the
wood chips. It only came out to the air of the world.
It came out of the fruit, but it didn't actually go on
the ground itself. What's the story? And the גמרא Gemara by all
of these says תיקו, teiku, we don't know. בעא רב אשי, Ba'ei
Rav Ashi, רב אשי Rav Ashi asked, לגג תמרה מהו? legag timrah
mahu? What's considered, let's say what's considered coming out? Let's say it
goes out of the date, but it's still like there, like you
know, in the top of the date. It's still sort of like,
so you know, I think they have like a little indentation near
the top, don't they? Where there must have been a stem, stem
maybe, right. I'm imagining that it means that like, you know, where
it sort of pops its head out but then would come back
in. It's never really like in the process of leaving. I think
we had that earlier, לגג תמרה. legag timrah. That seems to be
לאויר העולם. la'avir ha'olam. It's not exactly clear how this is different,
but the גמרא Gemara will explain why it's different. Let's take a
look. לגלעינותא מהו? legar'inusa mahu? Or let's say it never goes out
of the date itself, but it's just goes to, you know, goes
from the pit of the date and it goes out of the
pit into the flesh of the date, which is surprising, like we
were always assuming that even if it's in the flesh of something
it's okay, but apparently for dates the assumption is that they're growing
inside the pits and therefore maybe if it goes from the pit
into the flesh it's a problem. מתמרי לתמרי מהו? mitimrei letimrei mahu?
Let's say it never was exposed to air but it went from
one date to an adjoining date without going through the air. They
were pressed together. So is that considered that it's now שרץ על
הארץ? sheretz al ha'aretz? So the גמרא Gemara says תיקו, teiku, on
all these תיקו. teiku. So the issue about גג תמרה gag timrah
is the most unclear, I have to admit, or we're both unclear.
A, the thing about the pit, we've normally assumed that anywhere in
the fruit it's okay, but also the thing about the roof. Like
Michael says, didn't we just say that if it pops its head
out, but here there's an assumption that no, at least with this
insect, that's a natural thing maybe for it to go up to
the roof and come back down. So maybe that's not considered yet
having separated like the lip of the vessel that we discussed before.
I really don't, can't explain this in more precision. It gets more
complicated. Well yeah, the whole thing gets here exactly, all these things
make it a lot more complicated to actually go by the permissions,
especially now that we have the ability to be more strict. You
know, when תוספות Tosfos didn't have the ability, then you're more willing
to find a path to say that it's permissible. Okay, so now
let's take a look, okay but we're going to have to just
bracket that. We have five minutes to finish this off. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רב ששת בריה דרב
אידי, Amar Rav Sheshes brei de-Rav Idi, so רב ששת Rav Sheshes
son of רב אידי Rav Idi said, כוקיאני אסירי. kokiani asiri. Okay,
these כוקיאני kokiani which are a certain type of a what do
you call it, of a let's see what רש"י Rashi says they
are, what, worm, yeah, some type of worm, right. רש"י, Rashi, oh
I'm sorry, right, thank you. Worms that are found in the liver
or the lungs of an animal. So now we're going to have
the same question by the animal. If you find insects, bugs that
grow inside the flesh of animals, did they originally grow there and
they were not שרץ על הארץ, sheretz al ha'aretz, or did they
come from the outside? So he says these worms that are found
in these organs of the animal are forbidden. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama,
why? מעלמא אתו, me'alma asu, they came from the outside, they didn't
grow originally in the animal. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, מתקיף
לה רב אשי, maskif lah Rav Ashi, רב אשי Rav Ashi asked
on this, אי מעלמא אתו, ei me'alma asu, if they really came
from the outside, לישתכחו דרך בית הרעי, lishtakechu derech beis hare'i, presumably
how did they come from the outside? They were swallowed in the
food that the animal ate. So then why are they found in
the lungs and the liver? Why aren't they found in the intestines,
in the stomach and the intestines? So they didn't come from the
outside, they grew there naturally. איכא דאמרי, Ika de'amri, others say, אמר
רב ששת בריה דרב אידי amar Rav Sheshes brei de-Rav Idi that
we started with that position, כוקיאני שרי, kokiani shari, these worms are
okay. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? מיניה גבלי, minei gavli, they come from
the very, they are formed from the very flesh of the animal
itself. Now גבלי, gavli, רש"י Rashi says means grows, but it also
somehow means like are formed, and here we're getting to a more
explicit idea which the גמרא Gemara will make completely explicit in a
minute, of the idea that the flesh becomes the bug, which was
this belief before they disproved spontaneous generation, you know, that the flesh
actually turned into the bug. So they are permitted because they don't
come from the outside, they come from the flesh itself. אמר רב
אשי פשיטא, Amar Rav Ashi peshita, of course they come from the
flesh itself. דאי מעלמא אתו, De'ei me'alma asu, if they came from
the outside so they would have come through being eaten. דאי מעלמא
קא אתו, De'ei me'alma ka asu, לישתכחו דרך בית הרעי, lishtakechu derech
beis hare'i, why not find them in the large intestine or you
know, in the stomach? So therefore of course they came from the
flesh and therefore they are permitted. Okay, so now let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says. So you think that the גמרא Gemara is
going to conclude they're permitted because it assumes that they came from
the flesh itself. So the גמרא Gemara says והלכתא, vehilchesa, but the
הלכה halacha is, כוקיאני אסירי, kokiani asiri, they're forbidden. מאי טעמא? Mai
ta'ama? מנחיריא עיילי באושי, minyiraya ayili be'ushi, because when the animal breathes
it doesn't come through. eating, there's other orifices. It comes through its
nostrils. So when it breathes, these insects come through the nose and
if they come through the nose, then they're going to get to
the lungs and the גמרא *Gemara* assumed that the lungs were connected
to the liver. So that's why you find them in the lungs
and the liver because they come through the breathing. Okay, now that's
the end of that. Now we're going to get to this issue
about bugs that come in meat and the גמרא'ס *Gemara's* idea that
they actually were formed from the meat itself. Let's take a look.
תולעי דארני דבישרא אסירי *Toloy darna de-bisra assiri*. So these types of
bits of worms that are in the meat are forbidden. But דחיורי
*de-chivre* if they're in the flesh of the fish, שריין *sharyin* they're
permissible. What's the difference? So אמר ליה רבינא לאימיה *amar lei Ravina
le-imei* and רבינא *Ravina* said to his mother, איבלי ואנא איכול *Ivelia
va-ana echol*, if you find those worms presumably in the fish, hide
it, I don't want to see it and be disgusted but I'll
be okay to eat it because הלכה *halacha* says it's okay. Leave
it to a woman's heart. So אמר ליה רב משרשיא בריה דרב
אחא לרבינא *amar lei Rav Mesharsheya bereih de-Rav Aha le-Ravina*. Now we're
going to talk about why it's different. מאי שנא מהא דתניא *Mai
shna me-ha de-tanya*, how's this different from what we said, את נבלתם
תשקצו *et nivlatam tishketsu* you shall find, you know, their the flesh
of these bugs you shall abominate, לרבות את הדרנים שבבהמה *lerabot et
ha-darnim she-be-behema* which includes that even these bugs in the flesh of
animal meat are forbidden? So why are those forbidden and the fish
is okay? So אמר ליה *amar lei*, now you would think until
now the whole difference has been did it come from the outside
or did it naturally grow there? But now we're going to introduce
a new concept. Even if it naturally grew there when it came
from animal flesh it's forbidden. Why? הכי השתא *Hachi hashta*. Okay, I'm
sure you can. בהמה בשחיטה הוא דמשתריא *Behema bi-shechita hu de-mishtaryia*. The
בהמה *behema* becomes permitted when you שחט *shecht* it. והני מדלא קמהנו
להו שחיטה *va-hani mid-lo kama-hanu le-hu shechita*, since these were formed, the
שחיטה *shechita* did not make them permitted. באיסורייהו קיימי *be-issuraiyu kaimi*, they
remain forbidden. Now what does that mean they remain forbidden? If they
naturally grew in the flesh of the animal they were never forbidden
as bugs. But no. The גמרא *Gemara* is assuming here is that
they transformed from the meat. So they started as meat and meat
it required שחיטה *shechita* to make them permissible. Then they transformed into
bugs. But now what this really is is animal meat that hasn't
had שחיטה *shechita*. Because when the שחיטה *shechita* took place, they were
already distinct and they were already bugs and not meat. But because
they originated in meat, so they're not אסור *assur* as bugs, they're
אסור *assur* as meat without שחיטה *shechita*. So they're post-שחיטה *shechita* bugs.
Right. Or un-שחט *shechted* bugs. Okay, that's why they're forbidden because it
believes that they came from the meat, so they're forbidden not as
bugs, but as something that was originated as animal meat that hasn't
had שחיטה *shechita*. All right. אבל דגים *Aval dagim*, but fish, באסיפה
בעלמא משתריא *ba-asifa be-alma mishtaryia*, fish don't need שחיטה *shechita*. So since
fish don't need שחיטה *shechita*, even if they originated from the fish
flesh, so let it be fish flesh, fish flesh is all is
permissible even if you gather it. והני כי גבלין *va-hani ki gavlin*
and when they grew בהיתרא גבלין *be-hetera gavlin* they grew in as
permitted because they grew from fish flesh which is never a problem.
Okay, let's just wrap this up. תנו רבנן *Tano rabbanan*. Now we're
going to speak about the other sort of creepy things that are
forbidden. הולך על גחון *Holech al gachon*, things that go on their
belly, these are land animals that are forbidden, זה נחש *ze nachash*,
the serpent, the snake. כל *Kol*, anything, לרבות את השלשול *lerabot et
ha-shilshul*, even like types of like, you know, whatever, slithery things. Whatever
they are, so worms and other types of things. דדומה לשלשול *de-domeh
le-shilshul*, anything similar to the שלשול *shilshul*. Okay, so various types of
worms. Okay. על ארבע *Al arba*, anything that creeps on the ground
on four, זה עקרב *ze akrav*, it's a scorpion, you know, so
it sort of like, you know, it does its sort of like
waddling type of movement. כל הולך *Kol holech*, anything that goes on
four, לרבות את החיפושית *lerabot et ha-chipushit*. What's a חיפושית *chipushit*? רש"י
*Rashi* says I don't know what it is. Okay. ודומה לחיפושית *ve-ha-domeh
le-chipushit* and anything, is that what it says? In modern Hebrew חיפושית
*chipushit* can be like a ladybug. All right, fine. Okay. מרבה רגלים
*Marbe raglayim*, anything with multiple legs, זה נדל *ze nadal*. So רש"י
*Rashi* says נדל *nadal*, look at רש"י *Rashi* says second wide line,
מאת רגלים קורין לו *me'at raglayim korin lo*. So there you go,
centipede. מאת רגלים *me'at raglayim*, he says that. Okay. Okay. עד כל
*Ad kol*, anything with multiple legs, לרבות את הדומה ואת הדומה לדומה
*lerabot et ha-domeh ve-et ha-domeh le-domeh*. Anything similar or similar to anything
similar. Basically, anything that's not a mammal with split hooves, or a
כשר *kosher* fish, or a כשר *kosher* bird, everything else is forbidden.
Okay, so all other creepy-crawly things are forbidden. Okay. תניא *Tanya*, last
line, רבי יוסי בן דורמסקית אומר *Rabbi Yossi ben Durmaskit omer*, לויתן
*Livyatan*, the לויתן *Livyatan* that's going to be in the future סעודה
*seuda* for the צדיקים *tzaddikim*, דג טהור הוא *dag tahor hu*, is
a כשר *kosher* fish, שנאמר גאוה אפיקי מגנים תחתיו חדודי חרס *shene'emar
ga'ava afikei maginim tachtav chadudei cheres*. אפיקי מגנים אלו קשקשים *Afikei maginim
eleu kaskasim*, so the things that that are protecting it מגנים *maginim*
is the is the whatever is the what do you call it?
a scale שבו *she-bo*, תחתיו חדודי חרס *tachtav chadudei cheres* under it
is the חדודי *chadudei* of pottery like the cutting things of pottery
אלו סנפירים *eleu snapirim*, those are the fins שפורח בהם *she-poreach ba-hem*
like a piece of pottery that cuts through things and that it
swims with. הדרן עלך אלו טרפות *Hadran alach Elu tereifot*. Next פרק
*perek*. פרק שמיני *perek shemini*. אלו טרפות *eilu treifot*. Sorry. פרק שלישי
*perek shlishi*. אלו טרפות *eilu treifot*. Page 42a. Page 42a. משנה *mishna*.
אלו טרפות בבהמה *elu treifot bebeheimah*. These are the טרפות *treifot* in
a beast. נקובת הושט *nekuvat haveshet*. A puncture in the gullet. ופסוקת
הגרגרת *upesukat hagergeret*. And a severed windpipe. ניקב קרום של מוח *nikav
krum shel moach*. If the membrane of the brain was punctured. ניקב
הלב לבית חללו *nikav halev leveit chalalo*. If the heart was punctured
to its cavity. נשברה השדרה ונפסק החוט שלה *nishberah hashedrah venifsek hachut
shelah*. If the spinal column was broken and its cord was severed.
ניטלה הכבד ונשתייר הימנה כזית *nitlah hakaved venishtayer heimena kezayit*. If the
liver was removed and there remains of it a כזית *kezayit*, הרי
זו כשרה *harei zu kesherah*. It is כשר *kosher*. Let's read that
again. ניטלה הכבד *nitlah hakaved*. If the liver was removed. ונשתייר הימנה
כזית *venishtayer heimena kezayit*. And there remained from it a כזית *kezayit*,
then it's כשר *kosher*. Only if there remains a כזית *kezayit*. That's
what it means. ניקב המסס ובית הכוסות לחוץ *nikav hamases uveit hakosot
lachutz*. If the omasum or the reticulum were punctured to the outside.
נפלה מן הגג *naflah min hagag*. If it fell from the roof.
נשתברו רוב צלעותיה *nishtabru rov tzaloteha*. Most of its ribs were broken.
ודרוסת הזאב *uderusat haze'ev*. And the mauling of a wolf. רבי יהודה
אומר *rabbi yehudah omer*. רבי יהודה *rabbi yehudah* says: דרוסת הזאב בדקה
*derusat haze'ev badekah*. The mauling of a wolf in small cattle. ודרוסת
הארי בגסה *uderusat ha'ari begasah*.
And
the mauling
of
a
lion
in
large
cattle.
ודרוסת
הנץ
בעוף
הדק
*derusat
hanetz
be'of
hadak*.
The mauling
of
a
hawk
in small
birds.
ודרוסת
הגס בעוף
הגס
*uderusat
hagas
be'of
hagas*.
And
the
mauling
of
the
larger in
large
birds.
זה
הכלל
*zeh
haklal*.
This
is
the
rule:
כל
שאין
כמוה
חיה טרפה
*kol
she'ein
kamohah
chayyah
treifah*. Any
animal
that
cannot
live is a
טרפה
*treifah*.